<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-12-28T12:31:50+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">Why do so many statisticians think variables or residuals must be normally distributed in linear regression?</title><link href="/2023/12/28/Why-do-so-many-statisticians-think-a-normality-assumption-is-required-in-linear-regression.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why do so many statisticians think variables or residuals must be normally distributed in linear regression?" /><published>2023-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2023/12/28/Why%20do%20so%20many%20statisticians%20think%20a%20normality%20assumption%20is%20required%20in%20linear%20regression</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/12/28/Why-do-so-many-statisticians-think-a-normality-assumption-is-required-in-linear-regression.html"><![CDATA[<p>28 Dec 2023</p>

<p>In my time working in health science, I have been troubled by the number of times I have encountered statisticians and practitioners of statistics who are absolutely sure that the variables or the residuals in a linear regression should be at least approximately normally distributed, and the model is invalid otherwise.</p>

<p>This idea is completely false. In this post I want to explore why so many working professionals nonetheless subscribe to it.</p>

<h3>  Linear regression </h3>

<p>When statisticians say a model is ‘valid’, they usually mean that there is a set of assumptions that are plausibly approximately satisfied, and that are sufficient to guarantee that our parameter estimates converge to their true population values, and that the distribution of the parameter estimates is approximately known (usually normal), as the sample size becomes large. The latter condition allows us to estimate standard errors on effects. There are several slightly different notions of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convergence_of_random_variables" target="_blank"> convergence for random variables</a>, but the most commonly used is convergence in probability. An estimator \( \hat{\beta} \) that converges in probability to true population value \( \beta \) is called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consistent_estimatorl" target="_blank"> consistent</a>.</p>

<p>In the following, I will use the this notation: \( y \) is an \( n \)-dimensional vector whose elements are \( y_i \), \( X \) is an \( n \times k \) matrix whose rows are \( x_i \), \( \beta \) is a \( k\)-dimensional vector of parameters to be estimated, and \( \epsilon \) is an \( n \)-dimensional vector of residuals whose elements are \( \epsilon_i \).</p>

<p>In the linear regression setting, there are standard sets of assumptions that are sufficient to guarantee consistency. Note the plural - there are several. The first version you often learn while studying statistics is the following:</p>

<p><b>1. Linearity.</b> The data-generating process is of the form \( y = X \beta + \epsilon \).</p>

<p><b>2. Strict exogeneity.</b> \( \mathbb{E}[\epsilon \; | \; X] = 0 \).</p>

<p><b>3. No multicollinearity.</b> The rank of \( X \) is \( k \) with probability \( 1 \).</p>

<p><b>4. Conditional normality of residuals.</b> \(  \epsilon \sim N(0, \sigma^2 I) \), where \( I \) is the \( n \times n \) identity matrix.</p>

<p>Note that an explicity normality assumption appears in <b>4</b>.</p>

<p>However, several of these conditions can be weakened. For example, the following set of conditions is also sufficient:</p>

<p><b>1. Linearity.</b> The data-generating process is of the form \( y = X \beta + \epsilon \).</p>

<p><b>2’. Ergodic stationarity.</b> The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stochastic_process" target="_blank"> stochastic pocess</a> \( (y_i, x_i) \) is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stationary_process" target="_blank"> stationary</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ergodic_process" target="_blank"> ergodic</a>.</p>

<p><b>3’. Weak exogeneity.</b> \( \mathbb{E}[\epsilon_i x_i] = 0 \; \forall i \).</p>

<p><b>4’. Invertibility.</b> \( \mathbb{E}[x_i x_i^T ] \) is invertible.</p>

<p><b>5’. Central limit theorem (CLT).</b> \(  \sqrt{n} \left( \frac{1}{n} \sum_{i} x_i \epsilon_i\right) \xrightarrow{d} N(0, \Sigma) \), where \( \xrightarrow{d} \) denotes <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convergence_of_random_variables#Convergence_in_distribution" target="_blank"> convergence in distribution</a>.</p>

<p>Note here that the explicit normality assumption <b>4</b> can be ‘replaced’ by <b>4’</b>, which is much weaker and only requires \( \frac{1}{n} \sum_{i} x_i \epsilon_i \) to obey a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central_limit_theorem" target="_blank"> central limit theorem</a>. The most basic version of the CLT applies to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Independent_and_identically_distributed_random_variables" target="_blank"> iid</a> random variables, but there are many other versions that weaken those requirements.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[28 Dec 2023]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Eric Weinstein is the Tenacious D of high energy physics</title><link href="/2023/10/29/Eric-Weinstein-is-the-Tenacious-D-of-high-energy-physics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Eric Weinstein is the Tenacious D of high energy physics" /><published>2023-10-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-10-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/2023/10/29/Eric%20Weinstein%20is%20the%20Tenacious%20D%20of%20high%20energy%20physics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/10/29/Eric-Weinstein-is-the-Tenacious-D-of-high-energy-physics.html"><![CDATA[<p>29 Oct 2023</p>

<h3>  Who is Eric Weinstein? </h3>

<p>Eric is a podcaster who has most notably made appearances on the Joe Rogan experience (JRE). He received a PhD in mathematical physics from Harvard in 1992, and between 2013 and 2022 he was a managing director of Thiel Capital - <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Thiel" target="_blank"> Peter Thiel</a>’s investment firm.</p>

<p>Eric came to some public prominence after his brother Bret Weinstein was involved in an incident at Evergeen State college. The college had a decades-old tradition called ‘Day of absence’, where ethnic minorities students would not attend campus to highlight their contributions. In 2017, a twist on this was put forward where white people would instead stay off campus for the day. Bret was a professor at the college at the time and refused to participate, circulating an email detailing his reasons. A group of students marched on one of his lectures in protest, angrily demanding he leave campus. The protestors later met with Evergreen staff and subjected them to what I can best describe as a struggle session. The whole incident was quite extraordinary, and I recommend watching raw footage, for example <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a7s8IAOuumQ&amp;list=PLq9jO8fmlPecnlR18OOm98bETOojth_NL&amp;index=6" target="_blank"> here</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3q_YIGrsODc&amp;list=PLq9jO8fmlPecnlR18OOm98bETOojth_NL&amp;index=31" target="_blank"> here</a>.</p>

<p>After the incident, Bret was invited to discuss his experiences on JRE, and went on to host a podcast himself. Eric managed to get a slot on JRE following his brother’s successful appearances. He subsequently coined the term ‘Intellectual dark web’, to refer to a group of iconoclastic thinkers and commentators, including such figures as Joe Rogan, Jordan Peterson, Sam harris and of course himself.</p>

<h3>  Who are Tenacious D? </h3>

<p>A comedy rock band consisting of Jack Black and Kyle Gass. You may remember them from their timeless classic <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_lK4cX5xGiQ" target="_blank"> Tribute</a>, which tells a tale of their encounter with a daemon who demands that they play the ‘best song in the world’. As the now immortal lyrics go, they played the first thing that came to their heads, which just so happened be the best song in the world. However, they aren’t able to remember or reproduce the song after the fact, so we have to rely on their word that it was, in fact, the best song in the world.</p>

<h3>  What do Eric Weinstein and Tenacious D have in common? </h3>

<p>Eric fancies himself as an unrecognised mathematical genius who holds the key to the elusive <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theory_of_everything" target="_blank"> theory of everything</a> - the holy grail of theoretical physics that many brilliant but lesser minds have been struggling to find for decades. He calls his theory ‘Geometric unity’. If you sign up to his mailing list <a href="https://geometricunity.org/" target="_blank"> here</a>, you can read a draft of this once in a lifetime work of brilliance.</p>

<p>Alternately, if you, like me, are puzzled by the idea of having to sign up to a mailing list to read a theoretical physics paper, you can find a draft that was released in 2021 <a href="https://geometricunity.nyc3.digitaloceanspaces.com/Geometric_Unity-Draft-April-1st-2021.pdf" target="_blank"> here</a>. You can also find a lecture he gave at Oxford in 2013 on his theory <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Z7rd04KzLcg" target="_blank"> here</a>.</p>

<p>Spoiler alert: I would not recommend grinding through either of these, even if you have the requisite physics background. The high level summary is that Eric has definitely solved every major outstanding problem in high energy physics, but he just can’t quite remember most or all of the details.</p>

<p>It is definitely the best theory in the world though.</p>

<h3>  I'm confused by how that could happen </h3>

<p>You and me both.</p>

<p>Eric claims to have figured out the major detail of the theory back in 1983-1984, when he would have been just 18-19 years old and in the middle of a combined Bachelor’s/Master’s degree. If you weren’t already suspicious, this should definitely set your bullshit detector screaming. Modern high energy physics is ming-bogglingly complex, to the extent that even world recognised geniuses only started to make serious contributions at earliest in their mid to late twenties. The vast majority of 18 years olds doing physics degrees haven’t even begun to acquire an understanding of general relativity or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard_Model" target="_blank"> the standard model</a>, both extremely complex subjects in their own right that demand mastery as a minimal price of entry before you might even begin making modest contributions towards a ‘theory of everything’.</p>

<p>But Weinstein, a man who admits to not having any spectcalar technical ability, as an 18 year old back in the 1980s, managed not only to make a contribution, but to blow the whole thing sky high? And has kept the lid on this stunning development for several decades, for, um, reasons?</p>

<p>Right.</p>

<p>Eric claims to have pieced together his theory of everything from various documents he produced in that period. From his <a href="https://geometricunity.nyc3.digitaloceanspaces.com/Geometric_Unity-Draft-April-1st-2021.pdf" target="_blank"> draft</a>:</p>

<blockquote> As such this document is an attempt to begin recovering a rather more complete theory which is at this point only partially remembered and stiched(sic) together from old computer files, notebooks, recordings and the like dating back as far as 1983-4 when the author began the present line of investigation. This is the first time the author has attempted to assemble the major components of the story and has discovered in the process how much variation there has been across matters of notation, convention, and methodology. 
</blockquote>
<p><br />
Well, if that doesn’t fill you with confidence, I don’t know what will.</p>

<p>Eric also wants you to know that he has very carefully taken into consideration the immediate objection you might have; that in his own words he has been ‘working in near total isolation from the community for over 25 years, does not know the current state of the literature, and has few, if any, colleagues to regularly consult.’ On this, he has the following to say</p>

<blockquote> Every effort has been made to standardize notation but what you are reading is stitched together from entirely heterogeneous sources and inaccuracies and discrepancies are regularly encountered as well as missing components when old work is located. The author notes many academicians find this unprofessional and therefore irritating. This is quite literally unprofessional as the author is not employed within the profession and has not worked professionally on such material since the fall of 1994. If you find this disagreeable, please feel free to take your professional assumptions elsewhere. This document comes from a context totally different from the world of grants, citations, research metrics, lectures, awards and positions. In fact, the author claims that if there is any merit to be found here, it is unlikely that it could be worked out in such a context due to the author’s direct experience of the political economy of modern academic research. This work stands apart from that context and does so proudly, intentionally, and without apology.
</blockquote>
<p><br />
Well, seems legit to me. If Eric’s work contains errors or just plain doesn’t make sense, the theory is not to blame; rather it’s all just part and parcel of him being a rogue that operates outside of the traditional, stifling environment of academia. If you really think about it, that’s actually a strength.</p>

<p>Ok let’s delve into the abyss of his ideas.</p>

<h3>  Not even wrong </h3>

<p>I have watched <a href="https://youtu.be/Z7rd04KzLcg" target="_blank"> Eric’s 2013 lecture at Oxford</a>. I found it completely incoherent, obscure and lacking in crucial detail. Eric himself admits that he made errors in presentation that may have rendered the talk largely unintelligible. An appropriately trained physicist cannot, for example, sit down with pen and paper and check the maths. You can’t even extract much qualitative detail about the theory. It’s just a vague mess of poorly-presented, half-baked ideas.</p>

<p>So I was very excited when, in 2021, after almost a decade of prevaricating, Eric announced that he was releasing his <a href="https://geometricunity.nyc3.digitaloceanspaces.com/Geometric_Unity-Draft-April-1st-2021.pdf" target="_blank"> paper</a> properly detailing the theory. I wanted to see some actual maths.</p>

<p>I confess, however, that I haven’t made it through the document. It’s the sort of thing you could spend a very long time reading and be none the wiser at the end. It’s still vague, it’s still incoherent, and it’s still the sort of thing that does not remotely show enough promise to spend whatever stupid amount of time it would take to get through it and still not understand at the end because, as it turns out, it’s all nonsense.</p>

<p>What I do understand is that he wishes to consider a gauge theory defined on a 14-dimensional manifold (his so-called ‘Observerse’) consisting of the four known spacetime dimensions, together with a bundle of symmetric  \( 4 \times 4 \) matrices. The gauge group on this total space is \( U(128) \).</p>

<p>The physical motivation for doing any of this is completely unclear. But ignoring that, there are already big problems. In 1967, Sidney Coleman and Jeffrey Mandula proved the 
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coleman%E2%80%93Mandula_theorem" target="_blank"> Coleman-Mandula theorem</a>, which forbids combining internal symmetries with spacetime symmetries. There are some exceptions in the theorem, the most notable of which is supersymmetry. It’s not clear to me what Eric Weinstein’s feelings are on supersymmetry. However, his theory, to the extent that it is intelligible (it isn’t), is not formulated with supersymmetry. He offers only this cryptic line on the subject:</p>

<blockquote> The author finds supersymmetry unnecessarily confusing as an as-if symmetry and is uncomfortable saying much more about it. </blockquote>
<p><br />
I don’t know what an ‘as-if’ symmetry is, but if Weinstein finds supersymmetry confusing then he is really up shit creek, since his theory needs supersymmetry if it is to have any hope at all.</p>

<p>Then there’s the problem that most all attempts to include the symmetries of general relativity into a gauge group have. Namely, general relativity has diffemorphism symmetry, which is much larger than the local Lorentz symmetry these theories typically try to combine with internal symmetries. Efforts like Weinstein’s don’t even try to address that issue.</p>

<p>The theory is constructed on a 14-dimensional spacetime manifold. Zero explanation is offered for how our four dimensional spacetime is to be recovered.</p>

<p>Finally, Eric also hasn’t even attempted to quantise his theory. This is a major hurdle any theory must overcome in order to be consistent with well known physics. I guess Eric hasn’t gotten round to it in the last 40 years.</p>

<p>The most enlightening resources I have found on Weinstein’s own work actually come from other people - in particular, critiques <a href="https://timothynguyen.org/geometric-unity/" target="_blank"> here</a> given by Timothy Nguyen, who has a PhD in mathematics from MIT, was formerly a visiting assistant professor at Michigan State, and now works on machine learning at DeepMind. His <a href="https://timothynguyen.files.wordpress.com/2021/02/geometric_unity.pdf" target="_blank"> paper</a> is, in contrast to Weinstein’s, intelligible, and points out that the theory is a complete non-starter. The gauge theory it is based on leads to an anomaly, meaning there is no sensible quantisation. He also notes that</p>

<blockquote> Essential technical details of GU are omitted, leaving many of the central claims unverifiable. </blockquote>
<p><br />
I, for one, am shocked.</p>

<h3>  Some more metaphors </h3>
<p>It can be hard to fully convey how awful all of this to people outside the physics profession. I think the Tenacious D metaphor is pretty good. However, if it didn’t hit home for you, I have some others you might like.</p>

<p>The first is based on a South park episode in which the main characters find that an army of gnomes are stealing everyone’s underwear. When interrogated, the gnomes respond with their master plan illustrated thusly:</p>

<p><img src="../../../images/profit_meme.png" width="900" height="500" class="center" /></p>

<p>You can watch the sequence <a href="https://youtu.be/a5ih_TQWqCA" target="_blank"> here</a>; it’s very amusing. It’s also wonderfully apt as a metaphor for Weinstein’s theory, which is not so much a theory as it is a wish-list of magical things that do not exist but are required in order for his theory to work.</p>

<p>The other draws inspiration from the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bogdanov_affair" target="_blank"> Bogdanov affair</a>. The Bogdanovs were French twin brothers who found some success as television presenters and science popularisers. They obtained PhDs in physics from the Universiy of Burgundy around 2002. However, it soon transpired that their PhD theses were complete and utter nonsense. They contained some coherent mathematics copied from other papers, combined with what physicist John Baez described as</p>

<blockquote> a mishmash of superficially plausible sentences containing the right buzzwords in approximately the right order. There is no logic or cohesion in what they write.</blockquote>
<p><br />
Nonetheless, the brothers managed to fool some very smart people, getting five papers publish in peer-reviewed journals and even getting their theses approved by Dirac medallist <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Jackiw" target="_blank"> Roman Jackiw</a>.</p>

<p>Eric Weinstein is like a live-action Bogdanov affair. He knows enough about physics to lace his speech with technically correct, jargon-laden statements designed to give the appearance of deep knowledge, while combining with poetic statements about his grand ‘theory of everything’ that are ultimately either unintelligible or unverifiable.</p>

<h3>  How can this happen? </h3>

<p>Eric Weinstein has managed to get himself a voice on some very impressive platforms, including the Joe Rogan Experience, as well as stage time with some extremely accomplished physicists such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_Penrose" target="_blank"> Roger Penrose</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brian_Greene" target="_blank"> Brian Greene</a>. Which is really puzzling on the face of it, given that he has achieved next to nothing in the field. How does he do it?</p>

<p>Eric Weinstein’s main talent in life, it seems to me, is storytelling. Just watch him action when he speaks about a subject that isn’t physics. He puts together sentences that sound unusual, clever and interesting. There is a structure that can be followed, and you feel rewarded for following it. He speaks with confidence. And yet, when you break down what he’s actually saying into simple language, it’s typically vacuous or unintelligible or silly.</p>

<p>He also really likes to present himself as a maverick genius. A wonderful and cringe-worthy example of this came around the 20 minute mark on episdoe 1628 of the Joe Rogan experience.  They have the following exchange where a clip is pulled up of Weinstein playing guitar, which he clearly has some talent at.</p>

<blockquote>
 Eric: "I put out a brief clip of myself playing on instagram and I got contacted by some of the best guitarists in the f-ing world. When Tosin Abasi and Joe Robinson and Ryan Roxy contact you."<br />
<br />
Joe: "Give me some of this Jamie" (Eric's clip plays)<br />
<br />
Joe: "That's pretty good and you are doing that without a pick"<br />
<br />
Eric: "Yeah I didn't know you were supposed to use a pick.... apparently you are supposed to use a pick, but I didn't know! Basically I'm playing air guitar with a real guitar"<br />
<br />
Joe: "Wow that's really good. What do you mean you didn't know you weren't supposed to play with a pick?"<br />
<br />
Eric: "Dude I don't know what I'm doing. I don't know what I'm doing!<br />
<br />
Joe: "How did you learn how to do this?"<br />
<br />
Eric: "Ahhhh I hung out in a room, alone, sort of dark, and lonely"<br />
<br />
Joe: "Really?"<br />
<br />
Eric: "Yeah"<br />
<br />
Joe: "When did you learn this?"<br />
<br />
Eric: "This is part of the thing, I do a bunch of things that I don't do with other people, right? I just learn shit on my own"<br />
<br />
Joe: "But when did you learn this? How long ago?"<br />
<br />
Eric: "I don't even know, some of it in the last year"<br />
<br />
Joe: "But but when did you start playing guitar? You're pretending to be coy, and I don't like it, I'm calling you out on this."<br />
<br />
Eric: "Ok. I've had a guitar since I was 15"<br />
<br />
Joe: "Oh, ok you have been playing forever but you are self taught." 
</blockquote>
<p><br />
Eric is doing everything he can here to let the listener come to the conclusion that he picked up guitar a very short time ago, and now plays like a pro - a true autodidactic genius. Except Joe knows it’s just not possible and on this occasion nails him on it.</p>

<p>Eric pulls similar tricks when he talks about physics with Joe, but gets away with it because Joe doesn’t know how to call him on his bullshit. Eric knows that the vast majority of the audience have no idea what he is talking about, but frequently uses esoteric technical language liberally and unnecessarily anyway. There is only one reason to do this; to craft a particular image that elevates himself above others.</p>

<h3> High energy confidence tricks </h3>

<p>Geometric unity has been summarily ignored by more or less the entirety of the high energy physics community. That’s because it’s a whole lot of hot air. I nonetheless can’t help but think that Eric would prefer if the theory was being attacked by mainstream physicists rather than being ignored. At least that would imply he is a threat, which is more aligned with his self-styling as a heretic and renegade. He’d rather be hated than be irrelevant.</p>

<p>I actually have a real soft spot for unorthodox outsiders who come out of nowhere and prove everyone wrong. A big part of me wants an Eric Weinstein style story to be true. Unfortunately the ultimate truth is that Eric Weinstein is a very sophisticated social illusionist who appears to have bought into his own bullshit. And to an extent, I get it; I don’t think there is a person who has gone into physics research without privately harbouring the small glimmer of hope that they one day might discover something incredible and be declared the next Einstein. Every one of us had a crazy idea or two at some point that we thought might just turn out to be mad genius. Then we all figured out we were really, really wrong and had to eat a sizeable portion of humble pie. Most of us learnt the lesson that needed to be learnt from that. Eric Weinstein didn’t. He doubled, then tripled down. He is a man whose real talent is projecting an image of an unheralded, iconoclastic genius to people who have no way of knowing better. Unfortunately it’s much easier to create that illusion than to be the real thing.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[29 Oct 2023]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The church of expected utility theory</title><link href="/2023/10/03/The-church-of-expected-utility-theory.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The church of expected utility theory" /><published>2023-10-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-10-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/2023/10/03/The%20church%20of%20expected%20utility%20theory</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/10/03/The-church-of-expected-utility-theory.html"><![CDATA[<p>03 Oct 2023</p>

<h3>  What is expected utility theory? </h3>

<p>Expected utility theory was first influentially expounded by Swiss mathematician <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_Bernoulli" target="_blank"> Daniel Bernoulli</a> in the 1700s. It seeks to answer the question of how to weigh up alternatives that are uncertain. For example, say I gave you the option of \( £100 \), or a bet consisting of a \( 50-50 \) chance of receiving \( £250 \), how should you choose? While it may seem easy to answer a single question like this, it turns out that building a general framework for how to make such decisions is not so easy, and if you proceed naively you can easily come a cropper.</p>

<p>Bernoulli’s basic idea is that you should assign a number to how good each possible alternative is, multiply it by the probability that alternative will actually happen, and sum it all up. The result is called ‘expected utility’, and the theory instructs us to maximise it. In my example, let’s say the utility of a quanity of money is equal to the quantity of money itself. Then the expected utility of the certain \( £100 \) is \(  1 \times 100 = 100\), while the expected utility of the bet is</p>

\[0.5 \times 0 + 0.5 \times 250 = 125,\]

<p>In this example, the bet comes out on top. However, there is no reason we have to assign utility to be equal to the quantity of money received. Maybe the benefit we derive from receiving \( £250 \) is less than twice the benefit we would get from receiving \( £100 \). In this case, expected utility theory would instruct us to go for the sure \( £100 \).</p>

<h3>  The von Neumann-Morgenstern utility theorem </h3>

<p>How do we know that this way of evaluating uncertain prospects is sensible? Well, the theory got a major boost from a rather striking result proved by John von Neumann and Oskar Morgenstern in 1947. They showed that a decision-maker who behaves in accordance with four seemingly very reasonable axioms <i>must</i> be an expected utility maximiser. What are these axioms?</p>

<p>Let’s first define \( \succeq \) to mean ‘at least as good as’. We will call an uncertain prospect a <i>lottery</i>. We may also consider ‘compound lotteries’, which can involve some probability of receiving a good which is itself a lottery. For example, I might offer you a \(50-50\) chance of taking the bet above. A compound lottery consisting of receiving lottery \( L \) with probability \( p \) will be denoted by \( pL \).</p>

<p>The axioms are as follows:</p>

<p><b>1. Completeness.</b> For any two lotteries \( L \) and \( M \), we have either \( L \succeq M \) or \( M \succeq L \)</p>

<p>This is just saying that in any comparison between two lotteries, one is always at least as good as the other - there are no lotteries that are ‘incomparable’.</p>

<p><b>2. Transitivity.</b> If there are three lotteries \( L \), \( M \) and \( N \), with \( L \succeq M \succeq N \), then \( L \succeq N \).</p>

<p>This means that you can’t have rock-paper-scissor-like preferences. It is often said that someone who has preferences like this could be used as a ‘money pump’, because they will presumably pay some non-zero amount of money to go around in a cycle that ends where they started. They can be taken on that ride ad infinitum.</p>

<p><b>3. Continuity.</b> For any three lotteries with \( L \succeq M \succeq N\), there is some probability \( p \) such that \( pL + (1-p)N \sim M \).</p>

<p>Here, the symbol \( \sim \) means indifference, or preferring two options equally. The continuity axioms says that we can always ‘trade in’ utility for probability. For example, you can always be left just as well off as you are now by taking a lottery where you get something better with probability \( p \) and something worse with probablity \((1-p)\).</p>

<p><b>4. Independence.</b> For any lottery \( M \) and any probability \( p \), \( L \succeq N \) if and only if \( pL + (1-p)M \succeq  pN + (1-p)M \).</p>

<p>Notice that the \( (1-p)M \) appears on both sides of the equation. This says that tacking on some other lottery that you receive no matter what does not affect your preferences.</p>

<p>There you have it. If you think those four axioms are reasonable, then you sir (or madam) must be an expected utilty maximiser.</p>

<h3>  Evangelical economics </h3>

<p>It’s hard to overstate how profoundly this theorem has shaped academic economics. There is nary a subfield which does not employ expected utility maximisation as its theoretical workhorse. It has completely dominated economic thinking for almost 80 years, and no doubt will continue to for some time to come.</p>

<p>There have been inevitably been some challenges to its reign, but mostly on the grounds of its limitations as a description of human behaviour. It turns out that humans are quite fickle creatures, and you can get them to behave in ways that violate these axioms. Most prominent among the would-be usurpers is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prospect_theory" target="_blank"> prospect theory</a>, but it has failed to really make a dent in the hegemony that expected utility theory has in the field.</p>

<p>However, even ignoring that, almost no one nowadays questions the idea that expected utility theory is an appropriate framework for a ‘rational’ decision-maker. That is, maybe us lowly humans fail to live up to its lofty mandates, but it is still the correct ideal we should be shooting for, even if we are too flawed to hit the target.</p>

<p>I beg to differ.</p>

<h3>  What's your problem, Steven?</h3>

<p>My problems are two-fold, my simple-minded interlocutor.</p>

<p>I find it hard to take issues with axioms <b>1.</b> and <b>4.</b>, so I will leave them unbesmirched. It’s the other two that stick in my craw.</p>

<h4> Transitivity </h4>
<p>I know what you’re thinking. How can I possibly take issue with transitivity. Am I some sort of masochist who likes being used as a money pump?</p>

<p>No, I am not.</p>

<p>Let me give you a simple example of a hapless protagonist, let’s call him Dave, who is an unwitting money pump. Imagine Dave is hiring for a job, and he ranks candidates on three separate criteria: Intelligence, experience, and hotness (Dave may be getting a call from HR soon). Each candidate has a numerical score along each dimension. However, Dave, being the pitiable stooge that he is, cannot distinguish between differences of less than 4 units along any dimension. He is presented with the following three candidates:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: center"><u><strong>Name </strong></u></th>
      <th style="text-align: center"><u><strong>Intelligence </strong></u></th>
      <th style="text-align: center"><u><strong>Experience </strong></u></th>
      <th style="text-align: center"><u><strong>Hotness </strong></u></th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">Alice</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">6</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">0</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">Bob</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">0</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">3</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">3</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">Carol</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">3</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">6</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">-3</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><b>Alice beats Bob</b>  via the intellgence dimension (they do not differ by more than 4 along the other two dimensions). <br />
Similarly, <b>Bob beats Carol</b> via the hotness dimension. <br />
And <b>Carol beats Alice</b> along the experience dimension. <br /></p>

<p>There you have it. Dave is doomed to embark upon an ill-fated, infinite loop of increasing salary offers until he finds himself in the mother of all debt holes. And all because of his failure to notice differences of less than 4. What a twonk!</p>

<p>Of course Dave hasn’t really behaved in any way that should be considered irrational. We can imagine that a difference of 4 lies beyond the limits of human, or even machine-aided perception - it can be as tiny a difference as you want. We can also imagine that Dave is not a complete moron and notices he is being money-pumped before handing over his life-savings.</p>

<p>So much for transitivity. Next up:</p>

<h4> Continuity </h4>

<p>I will take this one down by way of the following hypothetical.</p>

<p>Imagine I offer you a lottery consisting of a marginal improvement to your current well-being (perhaps a gentle pat on the head) with probability \( p \), but otherwise you will be crucified. Expected utility theory dictates that there must be some non-zero chance of crucifixion such that you would be indifferent between taking this bet and continuing on your merry way. That’s right - anything less would be ‘irrational’.</p>

<p>I don’t know about you, but I completely reject that. Ain’t no head pat in the universe good enough that I’m willing to risk crucifixion for.</p>

<p>More broadly speaking, there is an issue for expected utiltity theory whenever there are more distinctly ranked alternatives than there are real numbers. From axiom  <b>3.</b> above, imagine that there are more incremental improvements between \( L \) and \( N \) than there are numbers between 0 and 1. Then it must be possible to map every single one of these alternatives \( M \) onto a distinct number \( p \) between 0 and 1 such that \( pL + (1-p)N \sim M\). But it’s not at all difficult to come up with examples where you run out of numbers. For example, imagine my preferences are such that there is no amount of tea that I would prefer over a minute of experiencing the euphoria of being deeply in love. Such a preference would run afoul of Mr von Neumann and Mr Morgenstern.</p>

<h4> Whence expected utility theory? </h4>

<p>If its flaws are so obvious, why does expected utility theory continue to have such a strangehold over the academy?</p>

<p>The main reason is that it’s simple, and it allows economists to feel all fancy because they get to use elementary calculus. If there is an expected utility function, then you can differentiate it to find stationary points. Put a few layers of makeup on that, and BAM, you have got yourself a paper sunshine.</p>

<p>Unforunately the reality of life is a little harder to grapple with than that.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[03 Oct 2023]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My review of Barbie</title><link href="/2023/10/01/My-review-of-Barbie.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My review of Barbie" /><published>2023-10-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-10-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/2023/10/01/My%20review%20of%20Barbie</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/10/01/My-review-of-Barbie.html"><![CDATA[<p>01 Oct 2023</p>

<p>I’ve decided to try my hand as a culture critic. There’s no way I was going to pay to see the new Barbie movie in the cinemas, so this is a somewhat belated review. There are spoilers ahead.</p>

<h3>  Barbie world </h3>

<p>The movie starts in the world of Barbie, which is plucked from the imagination of a young girl. In this world, the barbies are all amazing, do everything of importance, and live in perpetual bliss. The kens are a collection of irredeemable idiots who are consigned to hanging out aimlessly on the beach all day doing nothing. This is the matriarchal utopia.</p>

<p>After some singing/dancing about how great Barbie world is, it becomes clear that in fact there is something rotten in the state of Denmark. The happiness is too forced, the world too boringly perfect. There’s nothing to achieve - the barbies are effortlessly amazing all the time. Nothing to learn, no real adventures to be had, and nothing for the human spirit to contend with. Everything is shallow and devoid of meaning.</p>

<p>There is also the hint that maybe, just maybe, the kens are being mistreated. They’re in love with the barbies and it’s clear that their existence revolves around them, and they desperately want to do something to get noticed. The barbies, evidently not in need of no man, coldly reject and exclude the kens.</p>

<p>Ok so clearly the naive view of a matriarchal utopia is being critiqued here. That’s a sensible idea that anyone can get on board with. So far, so so-so (that’s right, a triple (or is it quadruple?) so (and that’s to say nothing of the now triple parentheses. BAM!)).</p>

<h3> Real world </h3>

<p>Through a series of fairly uninteresting story developments, both Barbie and Ken find themselves transported to the real world. Venice beach, California, to be exact. Both of them immediately start being ogled by strangers. For Ken this is a welcome development - he feels admired, like he is living in the reverse of Barbie world. For Barbie, not so much. She  receives a litany of unwanted sexual comments from various men, and is then groped.</p>

<p>A bit more of uninteresting story development later, and they end up parting ways. Ken, thinking that he is in a glorious patriarchy, walks into a fancy corporate building and demands a high-powered, high-paying job. He’s told that he will at the very least need some basic qualifications. Puzzled, he asks ‘Isn’t being a man enough?’ to which his interlocutor replies ‘Actually right now it’s kind of the opposite’. Here we have an interesting, tacit acknowledgement of affirmative action policies, now ubiquitous in the work place, that outright discriminate in favour of women and against men. Ken continues his search down the job hierarchy, trying to become a doctor and then a lifeguard, both of which he is summarily rejected for due his lack of any relevant skills or qualifications. Clearly then, the real world is not just a gender-flipped version of Barbie world, where women can and do walk into any job they want with no discernible talent. And we also have the first hint of the complete incoherence of whatever political/cultural message the movie is meant to have. But more on that later.</p>

<p>In the meantime, Barbie finds what she thinks is the girl from whose imagination Barbie world is drawn - Sasha. She expects a warm welcome, but instead receives a nasty tirade about how Barbie represents everything wrong with the world, including ‘sexualised capitalism’ and presenting unrealistic beauty standards for young girls.</p>

<p>At Mattel headquarters we join the board of directors, which is entirely populated by buffoonishly inept men. Apparently this is the only place in the real world where incompetent men can walk into jobs far above their station. They are informed that Barbie is on the loose by one of an army of male interns, who is treated like crap by everyone and seems to have a thoroughly terrible life. We’re again left with ideological whiplash - is the real world a patriarchy in which men are the oppressor class and women the oppressed class, or not?</p>

<h3>  Ken world </h3>

<p>After some more uninteresting story development, Barbie, Sasha, and Sasha’s mother (Gloria) find themselves transported to Barbie world. Except it’s not Barbie world anymore, it’s Ken world. Ken got back before them and has taken over. The once amazing barbies that ran the world are reduced to maids and mindless sex objects. Barbie is shocked and dismayed at what has happened. She confronts Ken, and for approximately half a second he actually shows a glimpse of depth to his character, yelling “You failed me!” in a way that sticks out as jarringly real in an otherwise painfully superficial movie. It doesn’t last long though, as he promptly goes back to acting like the awful, entitled oppressor he inherently is.</p>

<p>The barbies hatch an inane scheme to take Barbie world back from the kens. It is during this segment that Gloria delivers an impassioned monologue, which is so important that I’m going to reproduce it here in full.</p>

<h3> The monologue </h3>
<blockquote> It is literally impossible to be a woman. You are so beautiful, and so smart, and it kills me that you don't think you're good enough. Like, we have to always be extraordinary, but somehow we're always doing it wrong. <br />
<br />
You have to be thin, but not too thin. And you can never say you want to be thin. You have to say you want to be healthy, but also you have to be thin. You have to have money, but you can't ask for money because that's crass. You have to be a boss, but you can't be mean. You have to lead, but you can't squash other people's ideas. You're supposed to love being a mother, but don't talk about your kids all the damn time. You have to be a career woman but also always be looking out for other people. <br />
<br />
You have to answer for men's bad behavior, which is insane, but if you point that out, you're accused of complaining. You're supposed to stay pretty for men, but not so pretty that you tempt them too much or that you threaten other women because you're supposed to be a part of the sisterhood. <br />
<br />
But always stand out and always be grateful. But never forget that the system is rigged. So find a way to acknowledge that but also always be grateful. <br />
<br />
You have to never get old, never be rude, never show off, never be selfish, never fall down, never fail, never show fear, never get out of line. It's too hard! It's too contradictory and nobody gives you a medal or says thank you! And it turns out in fact that not only are you doing everything wrong, but also everything is your fault. <br />
<br />
I'm just so tired of watching myself and every single other woman tie herself into knots so that people will like us. And if all of that is also true for a doll just representing women, then I don't even know.
</blockquote>

<p><br />
This monologue has apparently moved grown women the world over to tears.</p>

<p>I admit that it almost moved me to tears also. Just not quite in the same way.</p>

<p>My first reaction was ‘Welcome to being an adult’. It turns out that people expect things of you. It is not unreasonable for people to expect things of you. There is absolutely nothing about this which is unique to women.</p>

<p>It turns out also that people have different opinions about stuff. No matter what you do, someone will think you’re doing it too little, or too much, or just completely wrong. Again, welcome to being an adult.</p>

<p>I’m also immediately reminded of Rudyard Kipling’s wonderful poem ‘If’, also reprinted in full below.</p>

<blockquote> If you can keep your head when all about you  <br /> 
    Are losing theirs and blaming it on you,  <br /> 
If you can trust yourself when all men doubt you, <br />
    But make allowance for their doubting too; <br />  
If you can wait and not be tired by waiting,<br />
    Or being lied about, don’t deal in lies,<br />
Or being hated, don’t give way to hating,<br />
    And yet don’t look too good, nor talk too wise:<br />
<br />
If you can dream—and not make dreams your master; <br />  
    If you can think—and not make thoughts your aim; <br />  
If you can meet with Triumph and Disaster<br />
    And treat those two impostors just the same;  <br /> 
If you can bear to hear the truth you’ve spoken<br />
    Twisted by knaves to make a trap for fools,<br />
Or watch the things you gave your life to, broken,<br />
    And stoop and build ’em up with worn-out tools:<br />
<br />
If you can make one heap of all your winnings<br />
    And risk it on one turn of pitch-and-toss,<br />
And lose, and start again at your beginnings<br />
    And never breathe a word about your loss;<br />
If you can force your heart and nerve and sinew<br />
    To serve your turn long after they are gone, <br />  
And so hold on when there is nothing in you<br />
    Except the Will which says to them: ‘Hold on!’<br />
<br />
If you can talk with crowds and keep your virtue, <br />  
    Or walk with Kings—nor lose the common touch,<br />
If neither foes nor loving friends can hurt you,<br />
    If all men count with you, but none too much;<br />
If you can fill the unforgiving minute<br />
    With sixty seconds’ worth of distance run,  <br /> 
Yours is the Earth and everything that’s in it, <br />  
    And—which is more—you’ll be a Man, my son!<br />
</blockquote>

<p><br />
The subject matter strikes me as almost identical to Gloria’s monologue. Here we have an inspirational rallying cry for men to take on the weight of the world, with all it’s ugliness and unfairness and messiness, to tread impossibly thin lines showing nothing but courage and fortitude. Meanwhile, anything of that sort directed at women results in lots of bellyaching. Hmm.</p>

<h3> The revolution </h3>

<p>Next, the barbies carry out their plan of emotionally manipulating the kens so they all end up fighting amongst each other, and signing in a new constitution that reinstates the barbies to power while the kens are distracted. However, in a moment of conscience and revelation, the barbies decides that things shouldn’t go back to exactly the way they were before. The kens, taking encouragement from this, ask if they can have just one supreme court justice in the new world. They are refused and instead offered a lower circuit court judgeship, which, being pitiful morons, they gleefully accept. So, no one has learned anything then.</p>

<p>Gloria petitions the Mattel CEO to create an ‘ordinary barbie’, who isn’t remarkable in any way; just a normal woman with a ‘flattering top’ that wants to ‘get through the day feeling kind of good about herself’. This, of course, naturally raises the question of what the women actually want. On the one hand, if Gloria is to be believed, then there’s nothing wrong with the real world, presumably full of ordinary, non-aspirational women like herself. At the same time the whole movie is premised upon the idea that the real world is an oppressive patriarchy precisely because there aren’t aspirational women taking up the mantle of resonsibility and power. So, should women be aspirational or not? If they are, they inevitably open themselves up to impossible expectations, failure and criticism, which Gloria’s monologue indicates she is not a fan of. What’s it going to be, Barbie?</p>

<p>In a final plot twist, and after much unintelligible navel-gazing about what her true identity is, Barbie decides that she wants to be a real woman in the real world. The final sequence of the movie shows her dressed in a business suit, being chauffeured to what appears to be a very important meeting, and steeling her courage with platitudes offered by Gloria and Sasha. What extraordinary trial is she about to go through? Perhaps she’s interviewing to be a CEO?</p>

<p>She walks up to a receptionst’s desk and proudly announces:</p>

<blockquote>
I'm here to see my gynaecologist.
</blockquote>

<p>Wow. End film. Roll credits.</p>

<h3> Final thoughts </h3>

<p>So the ending of the movie was terrible. But it also seemed like there was an obvious missed opportunity. Instead of the kens becoming slightly less second-class citizens than they were before, why didn’t the kens and barbies realise and become the team that they were always meant to be? Why didn’t they land somewhere between matriarchy and patriarchy, in a world where men and women are treated with fairness and dignity? Why didn’t everyone coalesce around the campfire singing the kumbayas of the thing we all agree on - a sensible notion of gender equality - in a poignant, heart-warming moment of gender-based unity?</p>

<p>Well, there is a large team of smart, savvy, professional, highly-paid, profit-driven individuals who brought the wonder of Barbie to our screens, and this ending is so obvious there is no way they didn’t consider it. Therefore I have to believe the reason they didn’t go for it is the same reason the broader messaging of the movie was muddled to the point of stupidity. They’re speaking out of both sides of their mouth in order to placate a capricious, irrational audience.</p>

<p>See, if we had the kumbaya ending, we might be forced to conclude that the real world is not a patriarchy at all. As Ken found out, it’s a place where qualifications matter. Presumably this is the arrangement that the kens and barbies working together would have converged upon - assignments should be based not on gender, but merit. Maybe in a meritocracy we could have by chance ended up with more kens as supreme court justices than barbies, and more barbies as doctors. Maybe the kens and barbies are intrinsically interested in doing different things with their lives and voluntarily make different choices when given the freedom to do so. But clearly such sexist claptrap cannot be allowed to stand, and clearly the real world is an oppressive patriarchy - that doctrine cannot be questioned. So instead of the happy ending we should have got, we end up with a crummy joke about vaginas.</p>

<p>In this movie, you will find just about every idea or theory about gender, feminism, men and women expressed to some degree or another. Radical feminists, moderates, anti-feminists, men’s rights activists, will all find something to sympathise with. Almost no one can be universally pissed off with the messaging. I can only conclude that this was intentional - the film-makers were pandering and looking to avoid controversy. If an idea is expressed that you don’t like or disagree with, you can simply ignore it, write it off as tongue-in-cheek, or put it down to the ‘complexity’ of feminism. However, the inevitable result is a movie whose message is utterly incoherent. Decades from now, PhD students in the humanities will write many theses about how this movie exemplifies how utterly confused the feminist movement of the current era is. I can just hear them furiously tapping away at their keyboards while they should instead be spending their time acquiring skills that are actually useful in the real world.</p>

<p>I would also be remiss to not say something about the male archetypes of the movie. Barbie falls rather predictably into the ‘trap’ that every recent movie with a feminist agenda has. Namely, every single male character is either despicable or pathetic. Sometimes both. The only difference is power - men who have it are despicable, and men who don’t are pathetic. These are the only two options that are dreamt of in their conceptual universe. The idea of an honest, wise, self-sacrificing man in a position of power, who wields that power responsibly and whom is fundamentally motivated by the benefit of others - for the writers, this is a fantasy. And that is a profoundly sad commentary on our current cultural moment.</p>

<p>This brings me neatly to my final point. Even if you ignore the stupid messaging and politics of the movie, it completely fails to deliver the number one thing that a movie is supposed to do: entertain. The characters are all vapid, they don’t learn or achieve anything, the story is uninteresting, the jokes are crap. What else is there? Usually when a movie grosses astronomical amounts of money as Barbie has (more then a billion dollars!), I can at least understand why other people find it appealing, even if I don’t myself. In this instance, I will forever remain completely baffled.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[01 Oct 2023]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">In defence of linear regression</title><link href="/2023/08/29/In-defence-of-linear-regression.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In defence of linear regression" /><published>2023-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/2023/08/29/In%20defence%20of%20linear%20regression</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/08/29/In-defence-of-linear-regression.html"><![CDATA[<p>29 Aug 2023</p>

<h3>  What is linear regression? </h3>

<p>It’s one of the first major topics you learn about when taking statistics class. In essence, it allows you to model the mean of a response variable \( y_i \) as depending on some explanatory variables \( x_i \), where the subscript \( i = 1…n \) labels different observations. More concretely,</p>

\[y = X \beta + \epsilon, \tag{1}\]

<p>where \( y \) is an \( n \)-dimensional vector whose elements are \( y_i \), \( X \) is an \( n \times k \) matrix whose rows are \( x_i \), and \( \beta \) is a \( k\)-dimensional vector of parameters to be estimated. If we assume that</p>

\[\mathbb{E}[\epsilon \;|\; X] = 0, \tag{2}\]

<p>then</p>

\[\mathbb{E}[y \;|\; X] = \mathbb{E}[X \beta \; | \; X], \tag{3} \label{ols}\]

<p>Multiplying both sides by the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moore%E2%80%93Penrose_inverse" target="_blank">Moore-Penrose pseudoinverse</a> of \( X \) gives</p>

\[\beta = \mathbb{E}[ (X^T X)^{-1} X^T y \;|\; X]. \tag{4}\]

<p>Finally, replacing the expected value with its sample counterpart gives the famous ordinary least squares formula</p>

\[\hat{\beta} = (X^T X)^{-1} X^T y. \tag{5}\]

<p>This is the most simple and instructive derivation of this equation you’ll ever see, if I do say so myself. And I do, in fact, say so myself.</p>

<h3>  What if you have a limited dependant variable?</h3>

<p>So, armed with the above formula, you can go about modelling all sorts of stuff. The technical assumptions being made are fairly unrestrictive. There is, inter alia, no assumption that \( \epsilon \) is normally distributed, as I have discovered is depressingly commonly believed even amongst professional statisticians (but that’s a topic for another day).</p>

<p>Ah but what if you want to model a process where, for example, the dependent variable \( y_i \) is binary, taking only values \( 0 \) or \( 1\), you say? The conventional wisdom is that you should not use linear regression, but a different model such as logistic regression. But a conditional probability is an expected value, which is exactly the sort of thing linear regression is meant to model. So why not use linear regression?</p>

<h3>  Objection 1: Out of bounds values</h3>

<p>You may have noticed that in equation \( \ref{ols} \), there is nothing stopping the modelled mean from being less than \( 0 \) or greater than \( 1 \). \( X \) and \( \beta \) might just conspire to make it so. Clearly that cannot actually be, given that \( y_i \in \{ 0, 1 \}\). This problem cannot occur in logistic regression, because the functional dependence of \( \mathbb{E}[y \; | \; X] \) on \( X \) and \( \beta \) ensures that the predicted values are always in  \( [0, 1] \).</p>

<p>To which I respond: if your model predicts a mean that is impossible by definition, then either your model specification is bad, or your sample size is too small. If you didn’t have either of those issues, then linear regression would be just dandy. It’s not the estimation method, it’s you.</p>

<p>In fact, you might even consider the foregoing an asset - predicted values that are out of bounds is a clear diagnostic tool you can use to detect issues with model specification and/or sample size.</p>

<h3>  Objection 2: Heteroscedasticity </h3>

<p>So usually we not only want to estimate \( \beta \), but also its variance, in order to have an idea of what level of confidence we can reasonably have in \( \hat{\beta}\). The most straightforward way of doing this makes the following assumption:</p>

\[\mathrm{Var}[\epsilon_i \; | \; X] = \sigma^2 \;\; \forall i. \tag{6}\]

<p>This goes under the name ‘homoscedasticity’, and means the variance of the residuals is independent of \( X \). It turns out that if you fit the model using linear regression, this assumption cannot possible be satisifed. The reason is that you are modelling a Bernoulli variable where the probability of a \( 1 \) is given by</p>

\[p_i := \mathbb{E}[y_i \; | \; X_i]. \tag{7}\]

<p>The variance of the Bernoulli variable is \( p_i(1-p_i) \), which in general will depend on \( X \), thus violating the homoscedasticity assumption.</p>

<p>Fortunately, there is a simple <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heteroskedasticity-consistent_standard_errors" target="_blank">estimator</a> for the variance of \( \beta \) that is ‘robust’ to heteroscedasticity, that handles this issue more than adequately.</p>

<h3>  What's the real reason you're not using linear regression? </h3>

<p>I am of course, not the first person to point any of this out. Otter Hellevik put forward the case nicely in this <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11135-007-9077-3" target="_blank">paper</a> from 2009, and others even before him. There are also other advantages that linear regression has over e.g. logistic regression. Interpretability for one - the coefficient in a linear regression will tell you the number of percentage points your risk for the outcome goes up as the associated independent variable increases by \(1\), whereas the coefficient in logistic regression will tell you an odds ratio, which is a lot less intuituive. I should also mention that similar arguments work for Poisson regression. There you are just modelling a rate, which is the expectation of a discrete random variable divided by time - something that ordinary least squares is also perfectly suited for.</p>

<p>Given all this, why does it remain more or less unthinkable in many fields for researchers to use linear regression in cases of a limited dependant variable?</p>

<p>I think one reason is that it’s a ‘zero-thought’ method. If you use linear regression when e.g. the dependant variable is binary, it just gives one more way that your modelling can definitively be said to have failed. No such thing will happen if you fit a logistic regression.</p>

<p>It probably also has something to do with the vagaries of history. Maximum likelihood methods are newer than linear regression, and were all the rage at the time. Plus computers have gotten a lot more powerful in recent decades, and often there is very little difference to the end user in fitting maximum likelihood models despite the fact that they are generally more computationally demanding.</p>

<p>One reason this may again become quite relevant, certainly in health data science, is if <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secure_multi-party_computation" target="_blank">secure multi-party computation</a> methods are adopted and become commonplace. These techniques allow a function to be calculated across multiple private datasets, with zero information sharing. However, nothing is free, and in this case it comes with a significant additional burden in computational complexity. That might make linear regression start to look very attractive again compared to methds that require iterative optimisation methods.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[29 Aug 2023]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Repugnant maths</title><link href="/2023/07/22/Repugnant-maths.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Repugnant maths" /><published>2023-07-22T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-07-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/2023/07/22/Repugnant%20maths</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/07/22/Repugnant-maths.html"><![CDATA[<p>22 Jul 2023</p>

<p>In a <a href="file:///C:/Users/Steven/Desktop/Git/personal_website/_site/2023/03/21/Population-ethics.html" target="_blank">previous post</a>, I discussed population ethics and perhaps its foremost unsolved problem, the repugnant conclusion. To recap, the basic idea is that if you believe a small loss in quality of life for a population can be compensated by adding some number of people with lives worth living, then applying the same reasoning repeatedly leads to the conclusion that there is some enormous number of people all leading lives barely worth living that would be preferable to e.g. one billion people all living superlative lives. That seems rather unpalatable to most people.</p>

<p>This problem has bamboozled philosphers for almost four decades, and single-handedly stymied any real progress in the field. Which is a rather puzzling state of affairs to me, since my initial reaction was that the solution is trivially easy. What, exactly, is stopping us from holding that there is no number of lives that are marginally worth living that would be better than the billion people in blissful content?</p>

<h3>  Not so fast, Mr non-philosphy-man </h3>

<p>So it turns out philosphers have thought about that already, and raised objections that in many quarters have been perceived as ‘fatal’. You can find a summary of the problem, and issues with various proposed solutions <a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/repugnant-conclusion/" target="_blank">here</a>. Of particular relevance is <a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/repugnant-conclusion/#QueWayWeComMeaWel" target="_blank">section 2.2</a>, which explains, with references, why apparently my proposed solution cannot work.</p>

<p>In particular, let’s suppose we have goods \( A \) and \( B \) such that no amount of \( B \) is better than a single unit of \( A \). In the literature, it is sometimes said that \( A \) and \( B \) are not ‘Archimedean equivalent’. Now imagine a sequence of goods starting at \( B \) and ending with \( A \), such that each good is marginally better than its predecessor. The claim is that there must be a pair of goods that are adjacent in the sequence, such that no amount of the slightly worse good is better than a single unit of the slightly better one. This is used as an argument against the existence of non-Achimedean equivalent goods because it would imply, for example, that one chocolate sundae with the perfect amount of sprinkles is superior to a gazillion (yes you heard right, a gazillion!) chocolate sundaes with a slightly suboptimal amount of sprinkles.</p>

<p>What pish-tosh is that! Clearly it cannot be!</p>

<h3>  Not so fast, Mr non-maths-man </h3>

<p>To the mathematically-inclined (i.e., me), it seems fairly clear this objection is nonsense. It would appear to imply that it is not possible to sensibly order an infinite set of objects. And yet clearly we can. What’s going on here?</p>

<p>Mr philosphy-man has made an elementary mathematical error, that I will attempt to illustrate by way of metaphor.</p>

<p>Imagine a child that can only count to 10. We ask the child to rank a set of 20 different toys, from least preferred to most preferred, using counting numbers. Once they reach the 11th toy, they become confused; clearly it is better than the 10th toy, but there are no longer any numbers left. The child trusting its maths ability more than the evidence of its own eyes, grudgingly concludes that there cannot be be a toy better than the 10th  toy.</p>

<p>Now fast forward a decade or two; the child has grown up and is a young adult. They long ago learnt about the number 11 and the folly of their previous reasoning. In fact they have become much more sophisticated; they have attended university where they encountered the idea of a sequence - a collection of set elements indexed by the natural numbers. Equipped with this new knowledge, we ask them to construct a sequence of every possible real quantity of money they might be the recipient of in order of desirability, starting with least desirable. They try map every real number onto a distinct natural number, and quickly discover that they run out of natural numbers before they have even covered all quantities of money between 0 and 1 pounds. Cheerfully, they proclaim there is no quantity of money that would be better than any quantity not yet assigned to the sequence.</p>

<p>This is analogous to reasoning presented by our esteemed colleague, Mr philosophy-man. Turns out that all that has happened is that he has run out of numbers. But that doesn’t mean the tectonic plates of reality must shift around him; it just means that he needs to take a few more maths classes!</p>

<h3>  Ordinal numbers</h3>

<p>This particular problem was solved more than a century ago by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georg_Cantor" target="_blank">Georg Cantor</a>, and developed further by e.g.
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_von_Neumann" target="_blank">John von Neumann</a>. The upshot is that if you want to order infinite sets, then you’re going to need 
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ordinal_number" target="_blank">ordinal numbers</a>. These include numbers that are larger than any integer. Again, allow me to illustate with an example.</p>

<p>Alice likes apples and oranges. She always prefers a larger number of apples/oranges to a smaller number. However, she likes apples more than oranges, to the extent that there is no number of oranges that she would prefer to even a single apple. We might try represent her preferences using numbers, by assigning 1 to the bundle consisting of 1 orange, the number 2 to 2 oranges, etc.</p>

<p>However, if we limit ourselves to the natural numbers, we immediately run into a problem. The bundle consisting of a single apple cannot be assigned a natural number in a way that respects Alice’s preferences. Whichever number it is assigned, there is always a larger natural number available, which would incorrectly imply that there is some number of oranges Alice would prefer to one apple.</p>

<p>The correct way to resolve this is simply to define an abstract number, called \( \omega \), that is larger than any natural number. Then we assign \( \omega \) to the bundle consisting of 1 apple. For 1 apple and 1 orange, we assign \( \omega + 1\), and so on. \( \omega \) is called the first infinite ordinal number. This construction can be made rigorous, and is foundational in set theory, which underpins all of mathematics.</p>

<p>Once you figure out that you need ordinal numbers, then Mr philosphy-man’s problem evaporates completely. We can now place \( B \) and \( A \) in a <b>transfinite sequence</b>, where they are separated by an infinite number of incremental improvements. And if, for example, we assign 1 to \( B \) and \( \omega \) to \( A \), then there are no two adjacent elements that are non-Archimedean equivalent, because \( \omega \) <b>does not have a predecessor!</b> That is because for any candidate natural number that might be its predecessor, there is always a larger natural number in between.</p>

<p>If you wish to read more about this, including more mathematical detail than you probably want, you should check out my recent paper <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=4469869" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<h3>  What to make of this? </h3>

<p>Perhaps the first take away from all of this is to not put much truck in philosphers, no matter how many degrees and professorships they have from Oxbridge or the Ivy league. This simple problem has dumbfounded the entire field for several decades, and it all rests on some bad maths. A normal person would not even perceive what the problem is exactly. It turns out that a very fancy and expensive education is a precondition for wasting your time on esoteric matters such as these.</p>

<p>More seriously, I am quite dismayed by all of this. In particular because there are philosphers who take such ideas seriously enough that they’re effectively willing to bet millions of dollars on them, directing funds towards causes that their moral calculus has led them to believe are the best uses of money. It ceases to be a laughing matter when there are serious real world consequences at stake.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[22 Jul 2023]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is vaccine misinformation?</title><link href="/2023/07/20/What-is-vaccine-misinformation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is vaccine misinformation?" /><published>2023-07-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-07-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/2023/07/20/What%20is%20vaccine%20misinformation</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/07/20/What-is-vaccine-misinformation.html"><![CDATA[<p>20 Jul 2023</p>

<p>In November 2021, I was invited by Health Data Research UK (HDRUK) to give a talk as part of a public webinar on vaccine safety. One of the goals of this webinar was to allow members of the public to ask questions and interact with professionals carrying out research in this area.</p>

<p>The event seemed to me to be relatively successful. I presented results from a study I had recently carried out, the main finding of which was an association between vaccination with Oxford-AstraZeneca and elevated risk of cerebral venous sinus thrombosis (a type of blood clot in the brain). This was followed up by some thoughts and open questions about policy-making that were meant to prompt further discussion in the Q&amp;A section. Videos of the presentations were uploaded on to HDRUK’s Youtube channel. I was happy with how everything went and hadn’t given a great deal of thought to it after that.</p>

<p>That changed recently when I learned that the video of my talk has been taken down from Youtube due to spreading medicial misinformation. That is rather a serious charge, which I intend to address here.</p>

<h3>  What was in your talk? </h3>

<p>I don’t have video of the talk, though I do still have the slides. You can see them <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1FBP1l_gJxqZHgY-wngBw3MFEfcjVZemR/edit?usp=sharing&amp;ouid=101718537881581550754&amp;rtpof=true&amp;sd=true" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<p>I don’t believe the part of the talk where I presented my research that has now been published in top peer-reviewed journals, could in any way be interpreted as medical misinformation. I therefore can only assume the offending content is on slides 13-15, where I discuss risks and benefits associated with vaccination, and possible policy-making implications. In particular my best guess at the culprit is the following slide:</p>

<p><img src="../../../images/D&amp;C open door webinar.png" width="900" height="500" class="center" /></p>

<p>Here again I consider more or less all of this content to be an uncontroversial precis of the state of our scientific knowledge; but perhaps it is the following bullet point that rankled:</p>

<blockquote>
Does being vaccinated reduce the chance you will transmit the infection to someone else?
</blockquote>

<p>Now this was, and still is, a perfectly valid question to ask. Vaccine effectiveness against transmission is an extraordinarily difficult topic to study, because transmission events are not well-recorded in the same way e.g. COVID-19 hospitalisations or deaths are - we do not have clinician-created records of when and why transmission events occur.</p>

<p>There are some also other very serious issues to contend with in studying vaccine effectiveness against transmission. One huge confounder is the fact that being vaccinated may cause people to behave in ways that increase their risk of contracting COVID-19. This was particularly the case at the time I gave the talk, because there were vaccine mandates in place that, for example, prohibited people from attending various public places if they were not vaccinated. Freedom of movement and association was essentially being offered up as an incentive by governments to get vaccinated.</p>

<p>Another big issue is the fact that vaccination may cause individuals to have much milder or even unnoticeable symptoms when they are infected, which in turn makes them less likely to engage in e.g. social-distancing practices.</p>

<p>This all means that there is not what I would consider strong scientific evidence on this question. By contrast, as far as effectiveness goes the evidence is rather unequivocal; there are a multitude of clinical trials as well as observational epidemiolgical studies that point to high levels of effectiveness against severe COVID-19 outcomes. This is simply not the case for transmission. And it was even more true at the time that the talk was given, when there were even fewer studies on effectiveness again transmision than there are now.</p>

<p>For these reasons, I considered this question to be completely fair-game, and one that had not been definitively answered in the scientific literature. I also considered it to be significant from the public health point of view to not encourage complacence on the part of people who were vaccinated, who might be less inclined to use masks, wash hands, observe social-distancing practices etc, as a result of a misplaced level of confidence in effectiveness against transmission not justified by the available evidence.</p>

<h3> If that is medical misinformation, what else is? </h3>

<p>If YouTube believes my talk constitutes medical misinformation, it is indicative of some very deep problems with their policies. They either believe that statements in accordance with a scientific consensus, or that honest raising of questions that have not definitively been answered in the scientific literature, constitute medical misinformation. Neither is a particularly good look.</p>

<h3> Has our zeal to suppress conspiracy theories fuelled the fire of conspiracy theories? </h3>

<p>Presumably part of YouTube’s motivation here is to suppres the spread of ‘conspiracy theories’. I have to say that I find the record of large social media companies on this front to be dismal and extremely worrying. As Joe Rogan has pointed out, there was a time when people were being suspended or banned from social media sites for spreading the ‘misinformation’ that you can still be infected with COVID-19 after receiving the vaccine. The idea that this is misinformation is now absolutely laughable, considering the huge proportion of people that have been vaccinated and subsequently contracted COVID-19.</p>

<p>The concern I have is that by vigorously suppressing discussion of completely legitimate questions the public had about vaccines, rather than quelling conspiracy theorists, social media companies may have emboldened and galvanised them. After all, if there is nothing to hide, then why did various authorities so fastidiously preoccupy themselves with curating what information the public can access and what questions they are allowed to discuss?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[20 Jul 2023]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Population ethics</title><link href="/2023/03/21/Population-ethics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Population ethics" /><published>2023-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2023/03/21/Population%20ethics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/03/21/Population-ethics.html"><![CDATA[<p>21 Mar 2023</p>

<p>Population ethics is a subfield of philosophy that attempts to sensibly compare two populations that may differ in size and material circumstances, and decide which state of the world is better. That is, if we had the choice between one of these states being a reality, which should we choose?</p>

<p>The way in which one answers these questions can have profound consequences. For example, if life is sacrosanct, then is there a moral obligation to have children? Is not having children when you could ethically tantamount to murder? Or, given the various risks that humanity faces, e.g. climate change, would it in fact be deeply immoral to bring more children into the world?</p>

<p>It also turns out that if you approach this topic in a naive way, you can get very confused very fast. People can end up accepting a series of reasonable-sounding logical steps that lead to conculsions that are, to say the least, extremely dubious.</p>

<h3> Exhibit A: The repugnant conclusion </h3>

<p>Let’s start in a simple-minded way. We’re given two states of the world, and we want to be able to decide which is better. We like numbers, so why don’t we try to assign a number to how ‘good’ each state is, where high numbers means better.</p>

<p>Presumably different people have different ideas about how good each state is, and will each assign their own number. We might imagine that the numbers represent some common unit of goodness - let’s call it utility. So for example, just as we all agree to measure distances in metres so that we can readily compare without having to worry about unit conversions, perhaps we can in principle do the same thing with utility.</p>

<p>So far, so simple.</p>

<p>Ok since we have a common unit of utility, maybe the natural way to aggregate is to add together. Let’s say in a given state of the world, person \( i \) has utility \( u_i \). Then the total utility is</p>

\[U = \sum_{i=1}^{N} u_i. \label{utility} \tag{1}\]

<p>Great, now we can begin to think about how we might use this utility function to make decisions about which states are better than others. This is where the fun starts.</p>

<p>Let’s imagine we have states of the world \( A \) and \( B \). State \( A \) has 100 people who have wonderful lives. State \( B \) has 100 people who have lives that are just a tiny bit better than if they had never come into existence at all.</p>

<p>We don’t need to do any moral calculus to think that \( A \) is clearly better than \( B \).
Ok, but now let’s add more people whose lives are just marginally worth living to state \( B \). If there were \( 10,000 \) such people, would \( B \) be better than \( A \)? How about \( 1,000,000 \)?</p>

<p>Most people’s intuition will tell them there is no number of additional people in state \( B \) that will make it better than \( A \). But that clashes with our equation \(\ref{utility}\). If we multiply any small, positive quantity up by a sufficiently large number, we can get a result that is as big as we want. That is to say, there is some number of people living lives that are just barely worth living, that is preferable to a smaller number of people living wonderful lives.</p>

<p>This is called the repugnant conclusion, and a lot of people don’t like it.</p>

<h3> Ok, so what did we do wrong? </h3>

<p>Maybe we shouldn’t be adding together everyone’s utility. Does it really make sense to do that?</p>

<p>The issue you have if you want to get rid of additive utilities is that you end up in situations where adding another perfectly happy person to the world isn’t any better than if you didn’t. Or adding a completely miserable person to the world isn’t any worse than if you didn’t. That seems like a non-starter.</p>

<p>How about this: maybe some states are not comparable to others. There is just no sensible way of doing it.</p>

<p>The issue with this is that it isn’t so much a solution to our problem as it is giving up. Remember we want to be able to decide which course of action is the best. There is no way of doing this if there are possibilities that are simply not comparable to others.</p>

<p>Ok then what’s left. Accept the repugnant conclusion? But now you can be led down some very strange roads. For example, you could justify inflicting extraordinary, undeserved suffering on people now in order to bring about a future that has trillions of people living lives that are marginally worth living. Maybe you’re willing to bite that bullet. I’m not.</p>

<h3> Hidden option C: We are idiots who don't know how to do maths </h3>

<p>Or, maybe the real place we went wrong was when we allowed philosophers to do maths. Ok, I jest. But more seriously, why should we use <i>numbers</i> to represent how good a state of the world is. Who says it should have anything to do with numbers?</p>

<p>Indeed, every decent economics graduate learns about the canonical example of an ordering that cannot be represented using real numbers: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lexicographic_preferences" target="_blank">lexicographic preferences</a>. In short, imagine I like both tea and spending time with my partner. However, there is no amount of tea in the world (or China) that would convince me to spend any less time with her. Those preferences simply cannot be represented using numbers. Turns out there just aren’t enough real numbers to accommodate/fathom my depths.</p>

<p>Ok, so why can’t we have lexicographic preferences or similar when it comes to population ethics? I.e. there is no number of lives that are barely worth living that would be morally preferable to 100 people having wonderful lives. Seems easy enough. We don’t have to come to any of the utterly bizarre conclusions that philosophers think are forced upon us. We just can’t use numbers to represent our preferences - we’re not such simple creatures.</p>

<p>It really is that easy. Nonetheless, you would be truly shocked by the sheer volume of commentary this completely trivial ‘problem’ has generated in academic philosophy circles. And if you’re anything like me, absolutely appalled by the moral positions that various esteemed thinkers take seriously and have adopted as a result of this thinking.</p>

<p>Never do philosophy kids.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[21 Mar 2023]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Effective altruism, longtermism and Pascal’s mugging</title><link href="/2023/01/04/Effective-altruism,-longtermism,-and-Pascal's-mugging.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Effective altruism, longtermism and Pascal’s mugging" /><published>2023-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2023/01/04/Effective%20altruism,%20longtermism,%20and%20Pascal&apos;s%20mugging</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/01/04/Effective-altruism,-longtermism,-and-Pascal&apos;s-mugging.html"><![CDATA[<p>04 Jan 2023</p>

<h3> What is effective altruism? </h3>

<p>It is a social movement that broadly aims to do the ‘most good’ in the world with limited resources. They advocate for making career choices and charitable donations that maximise altruistic impact. Their activities include writing research papers on ethics, analysing effectiveness of charitable organisations, giving career advice, and promoting pledges to donate a proportion of one’s income to charity. The main individuals who are credited with starting the movement are Will MacAskill and Toby Ord, both at the University of Oxford, and Australian moral philospher Peter Singer, at Princeton university.</p>

<h3> What is longtermism? </h3>

<p>Longtermism has become a signature idea within the effective altruism community. It broadly argues for greater emphasis to be placed on the long-term future in ethical decisions. The basic gist is that future humans/sentient beings who have not yet come into existence should be given the same ‘moral weight’ as those alive now. This tends to be coupled with the idea that the number of beings alive right now could be completely dwarfed by the number of future humans, especially if humanity survives for millions/billions of years into the future and colonises other planets.</p>

<h3> Sounds dandy. Ok, and what is the last thing you mentioned? </h3>

<p>Pascal’s mugging.</p>

<p>Let’s say you’re walking along the street one day and you’re accosted by a mugger. However, he is an extremely incompetent mugger who has forgotten his weapon. So, he instead makes the following proposal: give me all the money in your wallet, and tomorrow I will give you back twice that amount of money. You, being sensible, immediately dismiss his offer - what are the chances that he would actually follow through? The mugger, sensing he is losing you, continues to increase his offer. He says that if there is even the tiniest non-zero probability that he will honour the deal, then you should accept. Eventually he wins you over by offering a bajillion dollars on the morrow sharp if you agree, but otherwise he will kick a gazillion puppies right in the face.</p>

<h3> Ok, you have a problem, don't you Steven. Why don't you tell me about it. </h3>

<p>Yeah I do have a problem. Well-intuited, me.</p>

<p>The notion that we are not giving sufficient ‘moral weight’ to future individuals compared to individuals alive now, comes from a little mish-mash of undergraduate economics and philosophy. In economics 101, you learn that the default setting for economic models is to discount future utility. That means that we prefer a bowl of ice cream now compared to a bowl of ice cream tomorrow, or a year from now. This is expressed mathematically as follows:</p>

<p>\begin{align} U = \sum_{t=1}^{T} \beta^t u(x_t).\end{align}</p>

<p>Here, \( x_t \) is some amount of a good received at time \( t \) (e.g. a bowl of ice cream), \( u \) is a utility function which measures the benefit that you get from said good at the moment of consumption, and \( \beta \) is a number between 0 and 1 that we call the utility discount factor. The utility discount factor captures how much we prefer benefits now compared to benefits at a later date. For example, let’s say units of time are measured in days and \( \beta = 0.5 \). That would mean that a bowl of ice cream tomorrow is ‘worth’ half as much as a bowl of ice cream today.</p>

<p>Now, the fine upstanding philospher sees this and is frankly outraged. So outraged, he almost smashes his monocle. What does this presume to say - that the you of tomorrow has only half the moral worth of today’s you? What egregious claptrap is this!</p>

<p>I jest, but only a little. But that’s basically the longtermists; they think that \( \beta \) should be equal to 1, for reasons.</p>

<p>Of course what they completely ignore is that the utility discount factor is really just a parsimonious way of capturing the fact that everything is a lottery, without actually having to model everything as a lottery, because frankly that’s a pain in the arse. The choice is not between a bowl of ice cream now or tomorrow. It is a choice between a bowl of ice cream now, and an almost-certain bowl of ice cream tomorrow plus a small probability that you meet your tragic and untimely demise in an unforseeable bovine trebuchet incident before tomorrow, thus depriving you of said bowl of ice cream.</p>

<p>Ok I jest again, maybe a little more this time.</p>

<p>The point is there is a chance you may not be around to get that bowl of ice cream tomorrow, or you might lose your taste buds, or whatever else. Of course there’s also a chance that a magical fairy will wave her wand and make it so that tomorrow you get twice the enjoyment from that bowl of ice cream that you otherwise would have. But basically, there’s a lottery over events that could happen, and the end result of that lottery is that humans tend to prefer sure things today rather than near-sure things tomorrow, or not-so-sure things a year from now. As a quick fix to model this, we set \( \beta \) a little less than 1.</p>

<p>It is not difficult to figure this out. Many people know it, and have pointed it out. This has not stopped the longtermists from building a utopian (read: probably dystopian) moral calculus though.</p>

<p>So yeah, let’s say we take the longtermist idea seriously - there will be no utility discounting, no siree. On top of that, let’s presume that there is a non-zero chance that there will be an arbitrarily large number of human beings with wonderful lives in the future. Does this remind you of a certain unarmed robbery of a certain historical Frenchman yet?</p>

<p>Armed with this ideology, you could come to some rather dubious conclusions, to say the least. For example, you could argue that instead of using our resources to provide food for millions of people on the brink of famine today, we should instead give that money to our well-to-do academics and intellectual superiors at Oxbridge and the Ivy league so they can do urgently-needed research on where to best expend further resources.</p>

<p>Yeah, right.</p>

<p>In fact, you could use this ideology to justify inflicting any amount of suffering on people who are alive today, in order to serve the interests of hypothetical future people. After all, what’s worse: the suffering of a few million people, or the suffering of <b>ONE ZILLION SQUILLION</b> future people, who let’s face it are, for all ethical intents and purposes, really alive today.</p>

<p>This thinking is the product of ordinary academic minds furiously scurrying to justify their existence. They need some new, counterintuitive take that they can write papers about, use to position themselves as the thought-leaders of a burgeoning social movement and get tenured positions at universities.</p>

<p>It’s easy not to take this too seriously. Surely they are on the fringe.</p>

<p>Then you realise that that the effective altruism movement may have control over several billions of dollars.</p>

<p>Then you find out that a prominent effective altruist, by the name of Sam Bankman-Fried, was (allegedly!) running a cryptocurrency Ponzi scheme, which basically amounted to stealing people’s life savings and donating it to his preferred political party.</p>

<p>Very effective. Much altruism.</p>

<p>Really what this is is some kids with a god complex and a utopian ideology that, like so many before it, would almost certainly lead to misery on the grandest scale imaginable if ever fully realised. The only thing they need to make it a reality is a little more power.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[04 Jan 2023]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Negative vaccine effectiveness</title><link href="/2022/11/20/Negative-vaccine-effectiveness.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Negative vaccine effectiveness" /><published>2022-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/2022/11/20/Negative%20vaccine%20effectiveness</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2022/11/20/Negative-vaccine-effectiveness.html"><![CDATA[<p>20 Nov 2022</p>

<p>Myself and a team of collaborators including Stuart Bedston at the University of Swansea, Declan Bradley at Queen’s University Belfast and Mark Joy at the University of Oxford recently published a <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyac199" target="_blank"> paper</a> in the International Journal of Epidemiology studying waning of COVID-19 vaccine effectiveness. One of the major findings of the paper is that for first and second dose of AstraZeneca and first dose of Pfizer, effectiveness of the vaccine against COVID-19 hospitalisation or death reached zero by approximately day 60-80 after receiving the vaccine, and then went negative.</p>

<p>That is quite a striking result. This post is going to dig into possible explanations of this phenomenon and its implications.</p>

<h3> First of all, what did you actually do? </h3>

<p>We carried out a type of study called a ‘target trial emulation’. This attempts to find a ‘naturally occurring’ clinical trial, by matching people in a population who received a given treatment to similar people who didn’t receive the treatment. You can then compare the rate of adverse events in these retrospectively generated, artificial treatment and control groups.</p>

<p>The data that we used to do this study are highly confidential, and stored securely on different servers in each nation of the UK. It is not permitted to have any statistically disclosive, individual-level information leave those servers. However, we introduced an interesting methodological novelty that allowed us to do a pooled study despite these restrictions. This means that the final result that we ended up with is identical to what we would have got if the data all started out in the same location. We were able to do this because of the target trial emulation study design that we used. So, amazingly, it is possible to do a pooled analysis across multiple separate datasets that controls very carefully for individual level characteristics, without actually having to share any individual-level information!</p>

<h3> What could be causing negative vaccine effectiveness? </h3>

<p>One possibilty is that it is behavioural. So people who get vaccinated might be more likely to behave in ways that put them at greater risk of infection. For example, at various points during the pandemic, vaccinated people have been subject to fewer restrictions on movement than unvaccinated people. On the other hand, it could just as well go the other way - unvaccinated people may be less risk averse when it comes to the possibility of being infected, and thus may have behaved in ways that put them at greater danger of contracting COVID-19.</p>

<p>It is also possible that naturally-acquired immunity is more robust than vaccine-induced immunity. A <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyac199" target="_blank"> study</a> from Israel found that vaccinated individuals had a 13-fold increased risk of infection compared to previously infected individuals.</p>

<p>A final possibility is that this is all just a consequence of the fact that the protection offered by the vaccine is relatively short-lasting. For example, imagine that I had two cohorts of similar individuals, and vaccination offered 100% protection against infection for a short period of time. The first cohort receives a dose of vaccine on day 0, while the second cohort receives a dose of vaccine on day 30. One would intuitively expect that the first cohort would initially have fewer severe COVID-19 outcomes, but then at some point the second cohort would do better. Now instead of vaccinating the second cohort, let’s have them contract COVID-19. And instead of it happening on day 30, let’s sprinkle it around randomly in time, but initially occurring at a higher rate than in the vaccinated group. Finally, let’s assume that the vaccine is effective but not perfect for a short period of time, and naturally-acquired innoculation is as immunologically effective (or better) than the vaccine. One would still expect something qualitatively similar; the first cohort would have fewer events intially, then subsequently the second cohort would do better because those people who contract and recover from COVID-19 are naturally innoculated.</p>

<p>By the way I should say that our study is not the only one to find negative vaccine effectiveness - our result is unlikely to be an anomaly.</p>

<h3> What are the implications? </h3>

<p>If negative vaccine effectiveness is largely explained by behavioural factors, then it might be possible to curtail it with a public information campaign aimed at making sure vaccinated individuals continue to observe precautions against COVID-19. On the other hand, I do think that one of the major incentives to get the vaccine is so that one can return to normal behaviour. I personally am not convinced that the explanation for negative vaccine effectiveness is behavioural, and even if it was I am skeptical about our ability to do anything about it.</p>

<p>If negative vaccine effectiveness cannot be significantly curtailed, then it raises some very interesting policy questions. Vaccines still have utility, but what is their proper role in world where COVID-19 is endemic? For example, if vaccine doses could be timed so that the period where negative vaccine effectiveness would kick in happens towards the end of a wave of infections, it may be be possible to provide significant long-term protection by offering a precisley-timed, recurring regimen of COVID-19 vaccines. However, I don’t really have much confidence in our ability to sufficiently accurately forecast future waves of infections in a way that would allow us to usefully implement such a scheme.</p>

<p>The other main utility offered by COVID-19 vaccines is ‘flattening the curve’. That is, spreading the caseload over time so that our healthcare services are not overwhelmed and can offer better treatment. This could be worthwhile, though again it would require forecasting ability that so far has proven elusive to us.</p>

<p>The final question is whether all of this is worth it. Mass COVID-19 vaccinations are expensive, and it is not clear how beneficial it is. It seems quite possible that there are far more cost-effective ways to preserve human life. In particular, I think in our revolutionary fervour for vaccines, we may have neglected a cheaper and easier win in the form of anti-viral and monoclonal antibody treatments.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[20 Nov 2022]]></summary></entry></feed>